Guide to the University of Chicago. Harper College Center Rededication Records 1912-1973
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Harper College Center Rededication Records
1912-1973
2.75 linear ft. (4 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
In 1912 the construction of a new University of Chicago Library was completed. The building was dedicated in memory of the University of Chicago’s first President, William Rainey Harper, who died in 1906. The Harper Memorial Library was then renovated in 1973 and rededicated in conjunction with the renovation of Wiebolt Hall. Materials in this collection include programs, booklets, speeches, film media, and miscellaneous memorabilia associated with the 1912 and 1973 dedication ceremonies.
Information on Use
Access
Access to audio visual material may be restricted due to condition or lack of equipment.
Biographical Note
In 1902 the University of Chicago saw the need to construct a permanent central library. Plans for the new library were underway when the university’s first President, William Rainey Harper, passed away in 1906. To honor his service to the university, it was decided that the new library would be dedicated to his memory. Construction began in 1910 when the first cornerstone was laid. The building was completed in June of 1912, when the first dedication ceremony took place. Harper Memorial Library served as the main library for the university until the Regestein Library opened in September of 1970. At this time, Harper Library and Wiebolt Hall (originally constructed in 1928) were renovated to preserve their unique architecture and make them better able to meet the university’s growing needs. The rededication ceremony in 1973 marked the completion of these renovations and the transformation of the Harper Memorial Library from the university’s main library to the new College Center, designed to be the distinctive home for the undergraduate College.
Scope Note
The Harper College Center Rededication collection consists of programs, speeches, booklets, reel-to-reel, film, and other miscellaneous material associated with the original 1912 dedication and the 1973 rededication.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
University of Chicago -- Buildings; University of Chicago -- History; University of Chicago. Harper Memorial Library; University of Chicago. Library; Academic libraries
INVENTORY
- Replies, invitations to the dedication of William Rainey Harper Memorial Library, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Regrets, invitations to the dedication of William Rainey Harper Memorial Library, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Regrets, invitations to the dedication of William Rainey Harper Memorial Library, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Subscription to the Faculty Fund of the William Rainey Harper Memorial Library Fund, 1906-1909 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Program, cornerstone laying of William Rainey Harper Memorial Library, June 14, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Guest list, re-opening of Harper Memorial Library and Wiebolt hall, October 25, 1973, Program, re-opening of Harper Memorial Library and Wiebolt hall, October 25, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Program 346th Convocation, October 26, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Lectures, typed copies, Harper Lectures Series in conjunction with rededication ceremonies, October-November 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Lectures, typed copies, Harper-Wiebolt rededication ceremonies, October 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Slides, parade celebrating opening of the Harper Memorial Library College Center, October 26, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Administration information, misc. associated with 346th Convocation and accompanying re-opening of Harper Memorial Library and Wiebolt Hall (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Administrative correspondence associated with 346th Convocation and accompanying re-opening of Harper Memorial Library and Wiebolt Hall (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Booklet, "The William Rainey Harper Memorial Library with some account of the other buildings of the university," created for the dedication of Harper Memorial Library, June 10-11, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook, cornerstone laying and dedication of the William Rainey Harper Memorial Library (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Booklet, "The William Rainey Harper Memorial Library with some account of the other buildings of the university," created for the dedication of Harper Memorial Library, June 10-11, reprint, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Chicago Maroon, articles regarding re-opening of Harper Memorial Library and Wiebolt Hall, October 1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Posters, Harper Lecture Series and other campus events in honor of the rededication ceremonies (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Joseph Scwab, "Back-Talk from Abroad," reel-to-reel tape, Harper Dedication Lecture Series, November 19, 1973 (Box 4)
- Soia Mentschikoff, "Problems of Perception in Legal Contexts," reel-to-reel tape, Harper Dedication Lecture Series, November 5, 1973 (Box 4)
- Carl Hovde, "University College and Advanced Study," reel-to-reel tape, Harper Dedication Lecture Series, November 26, 1973 (Box 4)
- Joshua C. Taylor, "The Lost Art, or What Happened in the Grove," reel-to-reel tape, Harper Dedication Lecture Series, November 12, 1973 (Box 4)
- William Rea Keast, "What Happened to Liberal Education," reel-to-reel tape, Harper Dedication Lecture Series, October 29, 1973 (Box 4)
- "Rededication and Reopening of Harper-Wiebolt: at entrance to the Building, Dedmon, Levi, Oxnard, Weintraub," reel-to-reel tape, October 25, 1973. (Box 4)
- "Rededication of Harper-Wiebolt: Speeches at Cobb Hall (Quantrell Aud.), R. Hildrebrand, et. al.," reel-to-reel tape, October 25, 1973 (Box 4)
- "Rededication of Harper-Wiebolt: After-dinner speeches in Hutchinson Commons," reel-to-reel tape, October 25, 1973 (Box 4)
- Harper Dedication Parade, film, October 26, 1973 (Box 4)